i came across
a few similes about how one should
regard sensual pleasures
and how has a monk seen sense of
sensual pleasures in such a way that
they have no
underlying tendency for desire affection
infatuation and passion for essential
pleasures suppose there was a pit of glowing coals
suppose there was a pit of glowing coals
deeper than a man's height
filled with glowing coals that neither
flamed nor smoked
then a person would come along who wants
to live and doesn't want to die
who wants to be happy and recoil some
pain then two strong men grab
then two strong men grab
wood then two strong men grab would grab
each other each arm and drag them
towards the pits of glowing coals
then he would struggle to and fro
why is that for that person knows if i
fall in that pit of glowing coals that will
in that pit of glowing coals that will
result in my death or deadly
pain
and in the other simile
and how does a monk awakened to a way of
conduct and a way of living that such when they
and a way of living that such when they
live in that way
bad unskillful qualities of desire and
grief don't overwhelm him
suppose a person was to enter a thicket
full of thorns
that have thorns in front and behind to
the left and right
below and above so they so they would go
forward mindfully and come back
mindfully thinking
may i not get any thorns in the same way
whatever in the world seems nice and
pleasant is called a thorn in the
training of the noble ones
when they understand what a thorn is
they should understand
restraint and lack of strength
right so thorns and
burning embers and
well the main thing to mention there
it's like like that so the
the last the second simile so in the
discipline of the noble ones
means the person has the right view has
understood the four noble truths
they need to regard
every pleasure and nice thing as a thorn
and how what would that mean well that
would mean as if you are entering a
jungle so you have to enter the jungle and
so you have to enter the jungle and
there are lots of thorns around
so you have to be very careful
but the point to emphasis there it's not
that you have to learn how to be careful
you have to learn how to be careful
it's about you have to learn how to
regard nice things as thorns then carefulness
nice things as thorns then carefulness
caution they will come automatically you
will then be careful because it's
dangerous because if people would read i'm sure
because if people would read i'm sure
many people would have read that
similarly and then
mind would immediately kind of jump into
a conclusion that okay so
i need to be careful i need to move
carefully i need to do this carefully
yeah that's that's fine i mean you can
do that
but that's not what this similar refers
to
you would you could try and emulate
carefulness but it won't be the
carefulness that will result
in fulfilling of the noble discipline i
wouldn't result in other hanship
uh unless you learn how to see these
things as thorns
and that's why it says if you see things
as stones then you understand restraint
and lack of restraint in other words you
understand being careful and being
uncareful it's all rooted in in record it's
it's all rooted in in record it's
developing certain perceptions
in regard to things that would otherwise
be
a basis for sensual desire and so on
and same with with the glowing glowing
pit the suit that describes in their other
the suit that describes in their other
cities as well talk about it so
you your work your understanding your
discernment your sense restraint that you are doing
your sense restraint that you are doing
at the time all of the effort you put in
should be nothing i will never make a
mistake and i will be
always careful and mindful and watch
every turn i make
no it should be towards discerning how
to see sensuality
as burning embers then sense restraint
will be effortless
this passion will be outcome of it uh
non-suffering non-attachment will be the
result of seeing this thing rightly
of seeing this thing rightly
so the work is to recognize these
perceptions of danger
and peril in certain things
things that would otherwise basis for
desire as i said
and if you do so you will not need to
make the effort to restrain yourself it
will be preferred
and that's exactly in the first
simulation so that man
his mind his intention want to be
anywhere else in the world
except in the burning pit so when the
nice thing that used to be a basis for
centrality manifests in the mind of a
normal disciple
if he cultivates the perception of
danger in it as we would say if he sees
it as thorns and so on
he will not want to have it
so if he needs to eat for example he
will eat
as if he has to enter a jungle with it's
full of thorns that can really mess him
up
so he's very careful not careful in
terms of
the food specifically what he eats
but careful in how he perceive whatever
he eats
am i lapsing the perception of thorns
and embers and dangers that i have
developed the work is not i need to work harder
the work is not i need to work harder
i need to be more mindful of my
movements my thoughts my intentions my
all of this
you can do that but you need to work
harder in terms of
unobscuring the understanding
and the correct perception of what
sensuality really is consensuality is
factually like burning embers like
thorns if it weren't so you wouldn't be able to
if it weren't so you wouldn't be able to
free yourself from it so doesn't matter
how much you were trying to see burning
embers is just it would not be
compatible but because it is actually compatible if
but because it is actually compatible if
you keep cultivating this perception in
regard to it
and working your way through layer by
layer then you get to see it for what it is
then you get to see it for what it is
that's the danger became apparent
and now you don't need to anymore make
the effort to discern it now when
sensuality arises the danger is in its
core so there is no more confusion there's no
so there is no more confusion there's no
more doubt in regard to the nature of
pleasing and nice things in the world
doesn't mean you never see his smell
taste touch anything pleasing in the
world just means whenever anything pleasing is
just means whenever anything pleasing is
experienced the mind assumes the
attitude of a thorny jungle
because of that not because oh quickly i
must assume this attitude now in
response to this
no attitude of carefulness cautiousness
is automatic
based on the clarity of your perception
of thorn
amber danger it can harm me if i'm
careless if i allow that pleasure to to sort of
if i allow that pleasure to to sort of
become underlined for by craving for
more why why am i not seeing the danger then
why why am i not seeing the danger then
what's obstructing me from not seeing
the danger which is
which is a fact that danger is a fact
but i'm not seeing it
yeah you can state how the danger is a
fact but that fact is not true to your
experience because you still have passion because
because you still have passion because
if you understood
the fact of the danger in sensuality you
would be automatically
dispassionate so that's what you use as
a measure of your understanding so don't
because often people talk about this as
facts oh sensuality is dangerous it's like
oh sensuality is dangerous it's like
yeah but are you
now factually here and now free from
desire and lust or
anything pleasing in the world because
of the fact you just stated
if the answer is no means that's just an
abstract fact
which is fine in itself but often people
confuse their own abstract facts
for understanding well yes everything is
impermanent look a niche everywhere yeah
it's clear to me but i don't even have a
right view
i'm certainly not another hunt but here
i am talking about a nature that's
impossible if you understood on each even to the
if you understood on each even to the
basic level you'll be at least a sort
upon them that's what makes yourself
run so it's fine to have abstract ideas
and then obviously but the problem is
when abstract ideas are taken as facts
that now you don't need to do anything
about so in this particular instance it's even
so in this particular instance it's even
well the symptom that you have not
understood the fact of the danger of centrality is
the fact of the danger of centrality is
even more in your face
because multiple times during the day
you're going to be engaging with
centrality relishing welcoming planning voting on
relishing welcoming planning voting on
account of it
so it's just in your face just showing
you how not dispassionate
you are thorn arising exactly thorn
being recognized
carefulness induced embers presented
fighting these men that are dragging you
there automatic
so how how to recognize the danger
how to recognize well you have to take
it on trust first
so the buddha tells you the sensuality
is actually dangerous not worthy
clinging to
it completely contradicts your entire
experience so you have an option
this mr buddha or if you had enough
intelligence to see that
there's a good chance he's right because
in other things they said and because i
am dissatisfied with existence and
liability to do hands-on
you take it and trust so it is
unpleasant so
let me then see when pleasant pleasing
things manifest in my experience in my
mind first and foremost practice keep the
first and foremost practice keep the
virtue and practice sense restraint
so that needs to be taken on trust
initially if you do that then you will be able to
if you do that then you will be able to
allow these pleasing things to manifest
in your mind without you automatically
impulsively breaking the precepts and acting towards
breaking the precepts and acting towards
them and if you allow them to manifest
in your mind then you get to
and start contemplating and discerning
where how to what extent
it is dangerous because the peril is
there but it's not a parent oh this is a trap
but it's not a parent oh this is a trap
i'm entering this corridor but i've been
warned before
that this house this is how the traps
look like
i could dismiss the warning or i could
be very careful and understand the trap
before i get into it and thus i don't
get into it
if you understand how you're trapped
then i will learn how to walk through
this corridor
and not be trapped but if i don't even
know how i'm going to be trapped
i don't know what to be careful about
so sense restraint virtue needs to be
taken on account of that trust that the
buddha said something
even if that you don't necessarily see
but you accept the trust
but not as a goal in itself okay that's
it i trust the buddha
now they have accepted my sense
restraint on trust
i get to see that in regard to which i
need to practice sense restraint
i get to see the central thoughts
enduring in my mind pleasing objects
trying to
to overwhelm me and besets me and so on
and i get to then not act upon it
immediately which means giving in and
being trapped
dismiss them which means running away
and not passing through the corridor
that you do need to pass
sooner or later when you come back you
will come back carelessly and get
trapped again
and then you get to understand where
what that danger is
you can't understand it if you keep
denying sensuality or blindly engaging
with it
so it needs to manifest pleasing objects
you need to manifest in your mind
and you must connect out of it and you
must be able to endure it without
towards it or losing perspective and
then look danger what is the meaning of
look danger what is the meaning of
danger danger means what
pain can can you can uh like um would
you regard
danger friendly to you would you would
you regard something dangerous as pleasant
regard something dangerous as pleasant
no so there's a certain implications of
danger oh it wishes me harm it's actually
oh it wishes me harm it's actually
against me
it's trying to deceive me into this and
it's obviously unpleasant
the most obvious it's oh it's painful
so these are the implications then of
these pleasing state of mind
possibility of sensuality pleasing
thoughts that i have
that i'm enduring not anything out of so
i'm trying to descend the danger so
ah so this is actually not in my favor
to what extent why contemplate that
direction further understand it clarify
it
remove any doubt in regard to it
i mean i can tell you this is exactly
what the danger is but it will become
like another fact to the listener who is
not free from danger free from this passion
free from danger free from this passion
free from passion
uh so then they will just assume the
fact as if they are seeing it
in these things that's like yeah but is
that resulting this question no so you
just got a new piece of information
that's currently inspiring for you
but you want to have your own effort of
investigation of this phenomenon that
endure on account of you being sense restrained
on account of you being sense restrained
and not giving into it when it arises
and the danger will become apparent
the similes from the suta that the
buddha used will become apparent
the suit says how does he live in such a
way that he's not overwhelmed
by desire and grief exactly so so you
will not be overwhelmed
and that's that's in a way that's saying
also what the danger is
being completely overwhelmed oh yeah
sure sure so yes exactly why is this state
sure so yes exactly why is this state
that i'm enduring that i'm not giving
into where is the danger of it right here
where is the danger of it right here
right now not in 10 years not in 10
minutes danger should be apparent in that thing
danger should be apparent in that thing
that's there
pressing me trying to overwhelm me with
desire or grief or one way or the other you
or grief or one way or the other you
want to see the whole significance
exactly exactly that pressure then
taking the pressure so nobody denies
that there is there is a pleasing aspect
in consuming the bait
the bait is very tasty so that's not to
be denied
oh okay it's ugly no it's not it's
beautiful but there is a danger hidden in that
but there is a danger hidden in that
thing
that if you were to understand correctly
that beauty will be
unable to overwhelm your mind with
desire because
you will see through it
so what is that danger that is like
burning embers that will kill you that
every time you engage in centrality and
you have been doing
each time you've been re-exposing
yourself to it completely
ignorantly unaware of unaware of it and
making yourself because of that subject
to death
and suffering every single time so this
is the
dear herd simile that we always speak
about called the bait so
called the bait so
a deer trapper does not lay down bait
intending well-being for the deer herd
but instead he does so that the deer eat
the deer might eat it unwarily by going
right amongst the bait
and by doing so they will become
intoxicated and full into negligence
and then he can do with them whatever he
wants jesus so that's exactly what we
we just said like is this pleasing thing
that the the debate that you don't see
as a bait
oh but this is not for my well-being
if you know the traps are not set for
your good
so the sensuality then is not for my
good as i said you don't see that but the
as i said you don't see that but the
work is to see it to discern it in that
centrality in that which is beautiful
and enticing
and that you obviously automatically
because by seeing it is beautiful you're
automatically seeing it as friendly you're
seeing it as friendly you're
dramatically automatically seeing it as
non-threatening as harmless and that needs to change
as harmless and that needs to change
so like but why am i seeing this like
even that you don't know how to see
danger but
then question yourself that that which
you can you do recognize that sensuality
like say the something eating something
agreeable or seeing somebody agreeable
the pleasant aspect of it you you are taking
pleasant aspect of it you you are taking
it as harmless
why is that what is your basis what is
your justification for taking that
pleasure as harmless
where did you where did you get it who
told you you should
what is the basis for feeling absolutely
entitled to experience pleasure of the
senses like you know that's the most natural
like you know that's the most natural
thing well what is the basis for your
belief that is the most natural thing
where is that basis where did you get
that idea from you just assumed it
on account of what you don't have a clue
and yet here you are your whole your
whole world revolves around it
something that you haven't even actually
thought through but why am i regarding
this as pleasant
that's another line of questioning you
can apply on that same level why do i
think this is good for me
why do i no no what do i think why do i
already take this to be good for me
why am i already assuming that this is
worthy of desire and engagement why do i assume
of desire and engagement why do i assume
that pleasure
on that emotional level is not my enemy
millions of questions you can ask if you
have generated the right basis through
the sense restraint and virtue
then they'll start to pertain to the
actual sensuality that you're
experiencing enduring subjected to
and not acting towards so it's exactly
that oh the deer hurt
the the trapper does not set with the
well with a good intention
he sets the traps so to harm
whatever he wants to catch not to you
know make the life better
and they say oh so sensuality is there
to trap them
so why am i assuming that it's friendly
and see by doesn't mean like if if if
contemplating danger is too abstract
well contemplate that which you can see
which is your attitude towards this
which you want
it's wanted but wait why is it why is it
so wanted
why is it that i can't say no to this
why is it that i'm not in control when
desire arises
what is this pressure and the only
choice i have
is to give in or grit my teeth and not
give in
but why i do actually want to be why why
can't i just say
go away or stay now why am i not in that
position why am i being
overwhelmed i'm pressured pressured by
that and if you don't see that as a problem
and if you don't see that as a problem
well no amount of other buddha's
instruction will make any difference to
you because it is a problem the utmost the
because it is a problem the utmost the
greatest pleasure
it is overwhelming you you want it and
even if you get it you're the luckiest
man alive
yeah that's secondary the fact is you
are completely
under its thumb even before you
committed to it
and if that doesn't bother you means you
you you're ignoring the most obvious
way the hunter comes in
catches you drags you around and you
just pretend it's where you want to go
while the hunt is there in your face
laughing and torturing me
the fact that you are enticed full of
desire towards overwhelmed
overwhelmed that himself is that's well
that's that's the root of the problem
if sensuality would not be like that
you would not require or imply loss of
perspective loss of mindfulness and
everything else it would be wholesome
it wouldn't be underlined by more more
greed and more aversion and more
pressure
yeah so that the deception is there
that's why it's always compared it to a
bait to a trap
because it's deceiving it's not what it
seems like it's not what it shows itself
is it the enticement it's enticement
it's saying you know it's pulling you
towards look here
take it look look look we breadcrumbs
leading you to the to the prize
and you contemplate the nature of that
setup you will see the nature of the
the setup of central design the simile
of the deer herd
is trying to um it's about four types of
contemplatives four types of monastics
so the first deer hurt eat food
heatlessly by going right amongst the bait that the
by going right amongst the bait that the
deer trapper has set
and they get caught so like the first
type of mandicans
people who are unmindful and
unrestrained so there is no
any central strength there's no virtue
they just when desire arises they just
act by body by speech by mind they just when
by body by speech by mind they just when
the itch is there they scratch it
that's it so that's just normal that's
normal that's pretty much everybody here
and the second deer herd they see what's
happened you know to the first deer hurt and then
you know to the first deer hurt and then
they shun the bait
but instead go live in the deep forest
but when that food becomes too
scarce they come back they become too
weak and then they return to that bait
and eat heatly and get caught so that's
the the second type of people who
even without the buddhist teaching would
experience discontent
and um pain on account of that central
desire and they would have enough
intelligence to recognize it
so you don't need to like practice
buddhism to see that these
desires are fleeting cannot really be
satisfied are controlling your whole life revolves
are controlling your whole life revolves
around it and you know many people kind
of recognize like what's the point
so there are some who would then okay
let me do something about that
but then they shun the bait
see they so they got this this desire
said the sense desire the pressure or in
regard to the beautiful object
side sound smell test touches but they
don't understand
the root of the pressure the problem the
lack of they don't understand that
the mistake is yours in misperceiving it
as pleasing
not seeing the danger of it they think
the danger is
the problem is in the objects so they
they shun
all the objects so they determine that
they will never engage with anything
pleasing in the world
and that's the comparison to the run on
top of a mountain they would avoid
anything that could
entice them so you go into the
level of aesthetic practice where you
just deny any object of the senses that
could be pleasing
but the problem with that the pleasure
or displeasure is not defined by the
objects it's defined
by a state of mind so in other words you
can be living on top of a mountain
but if you haven't understood that
pleasure is rooted in your mind your
desire you will then even things that were
you will then even things that were
before displeasing
you go used to it and now the mind
relishes them and you start finding
pleasure sensuality in things that you didn't
sensuality in things that you didn't
used to
in other words something else starts to
serve as a purpose of a central object
because your mind framework is still the
same and you can't sustain that you cannot
and you can't sustain that you cannot
sustain that not engagement with sense
sensor or sense objects sooner or later
something pleasing will come up
you will see smell here taste touch
something agreeable
and given that there is no understanding
where the root of the desire is the
agreeability of these objects will mean
desire in my mind so that's that second
their herd when the grass
and and food runs scares and
they run out of it in the mountains when
they do get back to things they need to
do
see here smell they started they get
trapped because they haven't developed
any wisdom in regard to debate
in regard to the trap they only saw is a
trap let me run the opposite way but then
let me run the opposite way but then
they encountered a trap
and there is no knowledge of how to
avoid the trap
or rather not eat the bait within the
trap so if you know you enter the cage but
so if you know you enter the cage but
you don't touch the bait
you eat everything else you can leave
the cage mara won't see you
so some some people see the danger of
over indulging
yeah people would see the
dissatisfaction that comes
with sensuality especially if you keep
indulging sensuality this
dissatisfaction becomes obvious to
people that's what many people turn to
religion in general in spirituality and
meditation not specifically buddhism
because the dissatisfaction is not that
you know hidden and subtle
people see it but then what you how you
go about it
determines whether you still remain
within the same domain of the domain of
the same hunter
or you actually free yourself from that
because this is
so you you don't indulge
you you remain restrained some of the
time but then when things get difficult
but then when things get difficult
so you remain restrained on your own
terms like you know
but when the pressure is too much you
just you come down the mountain
and you go back to the base so your
whole say monday to friday
sure you have worked hard restrained you
haven't indulged yeah
yeah it's saturday sunday no it's just
or you do a
retreat retreat for a month but then
retreats over
and you're back to the so that's what i
mean you can do a retreat
you can be moderate and not indulge but
not for the sake of avoiding the bait
but for the sake of understanding the
trap so then when you can't sustain that
so then when you can't sustain that
environment of the mountain anymore
of that extreme withdrawal you still
won't eat unreadily you still won't take
the bait
even if the bait's right next to you you
will not take the hook
but for that you need understanding of
wisdom so yeah that's that's exactly that
so yeah that's that's exactly that
second type but many people would
revolve around that the first
impulse in somebody who sees the problem
with sensuality is to do
to shun it okay i will never engage with
centrality ever again
but as i said that determination you
cannot sustain that
sooner or later it will change generated
something against the will pleasing will
arise and pressure will overwhelm you just
and pressure will overwhelm you just
like before then you might try to double
down on your asceticism as giants did
and create all these extra elaborate
ways of avoiding but fundamentally you
are fighting the battle in a completely
misplaced field it's not there the
problems the route essentially are not
there yes you need to be sense restrained but
yes you need to be sense restrained but
the sensuality is not in the object you
are restrained against sensuality is in the
restrained against sensuality is in the
pressure that you cannot endure in your
mind the buddha would have outlined that
as a way of enlightenment
and he said himself if there was the
extreme practice of
asceticism and avoidance in the world i
have done it
to the point he refused to breathe he
didn't eat
he was so skinny he would grab his spine
through his stomach
and he said and none of that actually
freed me from sensuality
he tried it so if if there is anybody
who can rightly say i tried all this
i am the one he tried it for the purpose
of freeing himself from that treasure
and he didn't free him
and what is to say for those who didn't
even try that level of asceticism
and tell you asceticism is the way to
free yourself but they're not even
trying it to that extent
the buddha also thought it was the way
tried it before he was buddha to the
absolute outer end there was no more
than that to attempt
she said whatever pain to experience i
have experienced whatever
on a kind of endurance renunciation
asceticism self-torture
i have experienced no higher pain than
that and i tell you it was not
way to enlightenment it was not a way to
free me from desire
and that's when he started looking in
other directions
so it's inevitable to resist against the
bait but if you know enough you won't go too
but if you know enough you won't go too
far and waste all the effort climbing on
top of a mountain
just so to return back to the bait and
be re-trapped
you will actually start to understand
more and there's that
there was that story about
uh buddha in the past where these
ascetics were
having some conversation but the the
thing is
there was this practice whereby ascetics
would go up into the mountains for six
months and practice
extreme asceticism but then the food
over there would run out and then they
would have to come down again and then
get fed by the lay people good food get
fed by the lay people good food get
fattened up
for another six months and then go again
six months whatever
you know from time to time and it's like
that balance
well i will indulge but because i
renounce it's all equal it's all good means
it's all equal it's all good means
whether you're looking without
yeah whether you look at the renouncing
or you look at indulging you don't see
where the problem is
you don't see that the problem is in
that perception of centrality pressure
that you're under
not in object or saying no to the object
that's what i mean you mustn't be trying
to get rid
of the thoughts of sensuality in a sense
of like you shouldn't welcome
and entertain them and you must be
sensory strained beforehand
and value virtue established but now
when the thoughts arise if you get rid
of
it it's like i don't want to think about
a trap i mustn't think about the trap
but how will you then understand it how
do you understand then how you are
trapped you need to allow those thoughts to
you need to allow those thoughts to
endure because in themselves they are
not sensuality
your lack of restraint your action
you're choosing to act on a kind of
pressure that's where sensuality is there and it
that's where sensuality is there and it
would have said it countless times
because often people would just assume
oh it's this object so
any form of pleasure you get any form of
jaw you get on account of things in your
life or sensuality it's not
sensuality as the will said it's
basically not rooted in the beautiful
objects in the world
it's the man desire and lust that he
revolves around
that pressured desire i lust
that's why sensuality is in those
objects for another hand for the target
who has removed desire and lust in his
thoughts beautiful objects remain so he still
beautiful objects remain so he still
sees the beauty perceives the beauty
tastes the beauty hears the beauty
there's no lust in regard to it
and that's the the final deer hurt in
that same simmer
let's go to the the third
deer herd so the third
deer herd make their dwellings near the
bait and eat it carefully right but the deer
and eat it carefully right but the deer
chapman
then makes a barrier around the bait so
as to see where the deer come in and out
and then he finds the the herd dwelling
place so he doesn't yeah he doesn't catch him
so he doesn't yeah he doesn't catch him
on the kind of direct engagement with
the bait but he finds other traces that
they're left behind carelessly
and this is the same with contemplatives
who have given up
indulgence in external sense objects and
extreme aesthetic practice
but have not renounced internal
internally their desire for pleasure
they are physically restrained but not
mentally restrained
they act unwholesomely out of pressure
of views
yeah yeah exactly yeah the pressure of
views so
see that the third group of there they
saw engaging carelessly is a problem right
engaging carelessly is a problem right
over mining is a problem because
sooner you come back or you encounter
someone else and you get caught because
you haven't understood the bait
what if we stay nearby study the bait
and don't take the hook
but then they don't consider other
things that the trapper would see
and put brains like this that so they
don't learn how to be invisible
to mara so he gets and catches them and
they will compare those
basically traces that you leave to that
in like so you're not engaging
physically with it with the desire with centrality
with it with the desire with centrality
you're sally but you're perfectly
restrained but mentally you still entertain the
but mentally you still entertain the
same value
of of pleasing objects the same this for
them now you refuse to think about women or
now you refuse to think about women or
course sensuality
or you know breaking the precepts but
you think about other forms
for the same purpose you know stuff you
will eat how you will not be bothered by
displeasing sight sound smell taste
touches how you will build your little
palace protected by your whatever attendance
protected by your whatever attendance
how you will never experience any
hardship never experience any elements
so all that all of that becomes the
place for your centrality so all of that
still makes you very much concerned
about catering to your senses to your senses
catering to your senses to your senses
for pleasure
so then mara will the trapper will will
still get to see you
because you left all the footprints
around the bait and you just followed
them back
so they will compare that to these uh to
the like the the views
that you would have when you read when
the views are mentioned in the suttas
people often think on these like
metaphysical ideas about the world
about a life about the universe it's not
views it means
standpoints and opinions that you feel
blindly justified about
sometimes people say oh you shouldn't
hold to fix views
that's a view that is fixed so it's not
a choice
views are not a choice but what views
and how you
hold them that is a choice oh i will not
hold any views
because views are always bad well that
is your view that you just stated to me
thus you contradict yourself so you
realize oh you will have to hold the
views but are those views right views or the
but are those views right views or the
wrong views
are their standpoints and opinions
authentic transparent
not contradictory or not so practically
speaking views are anything
anything from you shouldn't be wearing
your old like that or
uh monks should get up at six o'clock or
we shouldn't be doing this you shouldn't
do that
and you will know whether you took the
view or not if by somebody who disagrees
with you
do you feel he will do you feel
irritation yes you're holding the views
even if it's the purest views on the
purest dharma
so so is the passion in regard to the
standpoint in regard to what should be done in
in regard to what should be done in
regard to how we should behave
is the real will if that's not met is
there irritation oh yeah that's why
trap still sees me i left the trail
so it's like when i say not holding onto
views it's not like
i i don't have an opinion on what how
much should wear the ropes no i do i
have hundreds of opinions
but if you disagree with that opinion or
if you prove that that opinion is wrong
my emotional state will be completely
unaffected so if you prove me wrong i'll gladly
so if you prove me wrong i'll gladly
accept that if you just disagree because
you're angry i'll just see you as a fool
factory either way i don't care because
i don't hold to these views
doesn't mean i don't have the views but
that's another thing the same principle
of
oh the essential objects are a problem
let me run on top of a mountain
oh the views are a problem let me have
no views
exactly the same thing people do the
same thing in regard to the views
try to not have them try to never have
them it's like but that is a view
now you're of a view that you mustn't
have any views
and so you contradict yourself you're
inauthentic completely
no have all the views you want they were
never the problem the problem was
basically underlying
emotional state of that view and
as i said you have the view the purest
view the cleanest view
and somebody comes and spits on it mocks
you for it
do you feel emotionally disturbed yes
means you are wrong to that extent for
holding that view
and that's why you're not free from sensuality
sensuality
so internally you have not removed the
passion so that's why it's it's subtler
so that's why it's it's subtler
obviously than
indulgence and complete asceticism but
it still
mirrors the same principle of sensuality
like do you
do you like do you realize the idea of
people agreeing with what you said
means you're emotionally invested in
your opinions and your views
you're the third type do you feel
threatened emotionally with the
possibility somebody will disagree
or disapprove of what you said you are
emotionally holding your views with
passion you are the third type no matter the
you are the third type no matter the
content of your view
the content of your opinion the facts
doesn't matter
are you indifferent equanimous in regard
to it as a basis or not
that's where the problem is that's why
you're not free from centrality
so that's it don't try to not have the
views just try to not be moved by them
and then you will also not lose
perspective because you will not hold on
to views now
for the emotional protection but you
will actually be able to
wait a minute i'm having these views but
artistry is right
and then you look and you find out
you're wrong and you will not be
threatened because often people are threatened by
because often people are threatened by
experience by
hearing the opposing opinion on some
important topic
they feel existentially threatened and
this you know often you hear that
like oh you know this mustn't be said
no anything can be said what's the
problem with
you're going to try preventing people
from saying things it's impossible
because they hold on to the view so much
that just the thought of the opposing
view fills them with anxiety but actually if
fills them with anxiety but actually if
you stop holding on to your views nopes
try to not have them you get to
understand and then you actually get to
explore and push the directions that you were
and push the directions that you were
afraid to before and actually that's how
you also get to abandon the wrong views
of a petunia
you need to be fearless because
fundamentally you are not a sotapanna because you
you are not a sotapanna because you
regard yourself
as the owner of yourself as permanent
suitable for pleasure
all these things so if these worldly
views upset you
how much more you're going to be upset
emotionally if you start underlining
your existential views
so that's why it's necessary to start
seeing that
there is no emotional justification
for any view that you have right or
wrong don't matter
if there is an emotional response
emotional basis emotional involvement
you are wrong
so if you can get upset on account of
what somebody said you are wrong
doesn't matter if they are completely
idiot doesn't matter from your point of
view from your point of if you're
interested in practice
you are wrong if you have emotional
investment in any view in any opinion in
any standpoint
and that's so that's obviously what so
that's how you become careful
in regard to the views and stand points
that you have that you have to have and
that's how you learn to not leave the
tracks and you become the fourth fourth type of
and you become the fourth fourth type of
herd
i mean the buddha if you judge by the
quantity of views
he had a view and opinion on everything
dhamma non-dhamma
but what he didn't have is passion
underlying any of it
so the fourth dear herd
make their dwellings where the deer
trapper cannot go
and thus cannot be caught so those
are the contemplatives who are both
externally and internally
internally restrained they did not act
out a pressure craving
and they developed ghana they place the
place where
mara cannot generalize
so that's the only successful group so
there is basically a
refusing to accept and give in and
welcome and attend any external
justification for yourself for your
standpoint that's how you become the fourth see the
that's how you become the fourth see the
third type
uses views and opinions about what
should be done sense restraint and
virtual that's important
but they take that as justifica
self-justifying so they built their place well within
so they built their place well within
the grounds that matter can enter
but if you say well even that the most
obvious factual thing you do need to be
sense restraining people keep the virtue
that's in my view my opinion
that it's factually right if you want to
practice the dhamma but
emotionally i'm not invested in it and
that's how you build the shelter
where mara will not see you you're
invisible to the trapper
to the hunter and that's the genre we
spoke about in all the previous talk as
well so not acting out learning how to endure
so not acting out learning how to endure
first and then abide in that state
of non-acting non-stand points
not revolving around this should be done
that should be done if the mind does
you don't take it up you'll let it
happen or you don't act out of it
and you are withdrawing from the modest
domain
invisible become invisible